What are banks? Like what function at their core for society do banks perform?
Wow, I love that question. I have to put a plug in before I even answer it for the book that I
wrote about a decade ago with Steve Haber called Fragile by Design, which is about the modern era
from the perspective of banks. That is understanding the history of the world from the perspective of
something that started about 400 years ago, which is the chartering of banks.
So the first thing in answering your question that somebody has to do is decide whether they
want to talk about a generic thing called financial intermediary that does some kinds of
transactions involving lending, maybe, or maybe payments transfers, or maybe both, or maybe managing
a portfolio, or maybe who knows what financial transactions. So by that sort of definition,
the Rothschilds were clearly a bank. They were a private bank. Lots of other, the Medici were a bank.
But when I use the term bank, generally, that's not the way I use it. I use it to talk about
a modern element. That is, when I say modern, I mean something about the modern world starting
around 1600 that distinguishes this world from its prior worlds. And the reason I focus on that
way of thinking is that the nation state created by the modern world charters banks,
and it's the chartering of banks that makes them in my mind so interesting, not just as an economic
function, but as a political reality. Now, I want to really emphasize every nation state charters
banks, by the way, not every nation state taxes. Kuwait doesn't tax. Not every nation state has
an army, Costa Rica doesn't have an army, but every nation state charters banks. Banks are
the cynical unknown of the nation state because it tells you something about the way of organizing
the world with power that a nation state creates rules for the existence of banks that it regulates.
The chartering of banks is all about deciding as a nation state that the functions of banks
have to be ruled by the political nation. Those, that is what a bank is. So that bank has done
lots of different kinds of transactions. Economic theory can illuminate why banks combine different
transactions. But if you don't start from the political reality, that the modern nation state
charters banks and regulates them for its political purposes, you're never going to get
really very far in understanding how banking systems evolve. Because banking systems don't
evolve through some sort of automatic process. They evolve under the restrictions and under
the opportunities that are provided by the nation state. That can be an opportunity if the nation
state charters a bank like the Bank of England, whose sole mission when it was chartered was to
help organize the finances of the state so that it could fight France. That was the point of
chartering the Bank of England. Wasn't so you, Ryan, could do something that you wanted to do?
And by the way, that bank was given a monopoly in England and Wales over
no creation, that is, you know, printing money. And so that wasn't a coincidence either.
That was part of the partnership between the people who operated the bank and the sovereign.
There's no way to understand the history of banking in England without taking into account
that banks weren't allowed to exist in effect, except as small private entities,
very small. They were restricted in their size if they weren't the one the state chartered.
So a bank, yes, okay, we can now talk about all the functions that banks may or may not do,
depending on what the sovereign allows. And we can also talk about shadow banks.
The banks that aren't chartered by the sovereign, which just do any kind of financial transactions
that they can get away with if they're not prohibited. But we don't start off. If you start off talking
about banks as some kind of natural abstract idea, you've really missed the boat. In the
modern era, banks are either, and this is the most important one, chartered entities of the state,
or things that operate in the shadow if they can get away with it and aren't prohibited by the state.
All of them do financial transactions. But if you don't start with the state, you don't
have a prayer of understanding what's going on. In the Wild West of DeFi, stability and innovation
are everything, which is why you should check out FRAC's finance, the protocol revolutionizing
stablecoins, DeFi, and Rolex. The core of FRAC's finance is FRAC's USD, which is backed by Blackrock's
Institutional Biddle Fund. FRAC's designed FRAC's USD for best-in-class yields across DeFi, T-bills,
and carry trade returns all in one. Just head to FRAC's.com, then stake it to earn some of the best
yields in DeFi. Want even more? Bridge your FRAC's USD over to the FRAC's USD for the same yield,
plus FRAC's USD points, and explore FRAC's diverse Layer 2 ecosystem with protocols like
Curve, Convex, and more, all rewarding early adopters. FRAC's isn't just a protocol,
it's a digital nation, powered by the FXS token and governed by its global community.
Acquire FXS through FRAC's.com or your go-to decks, stake it, and help shape FRAC's nation's future.
Ready to join the forefront of DeFi? Visit FRAC's.com now to start earning with FRAC's USD and
staked FRAC's USD, and for bankless listeners, you can use FRAC's.com/r/bankless when bridging
to FRAC's for exclusive FRAC's perks and boosted rewards. Ethereum's Layer 2 universe is exploding
with choices, but if you're looking for the best place to park and move your tokens, make
your next stop, UniChain. First, Liquidity. UniChain hosts the most liquid Uniswap V4 deployment on
any Layer 2, giving you deeper pools for flagship pairs like ETH/USDC. More liquidity means better
prices, less slippage, and smoother swaps, exactly what traders crave. The numbers back it up.
UniChain leads all Layer 2s in total value-locked for Uniswap V4, and it's not just deep, it's fast
and fully transparent, purpose-built to be the home base for DeFi and cross-chain liquidity.
When it comes to costs, UniChain is a no-brainer. Transaction fees come in about 95% cheaper than
Ethereum may net, slashing the price of creating or accessing liquidity. Want to stay in the loop
on UniChain? Visit unichain.org or follow @Unichain on X for all the updates. Introducing KGen,
aka Verify, the world's largest verified distribution protocol, or VDP. If you're trying to grow a
real protocol or app, you need real users doing real actions. If it's not, Verify is just noise.
At the core of Verify is poggy, KGen's identity and reputation framework. It helps you reach humans,
not bots, and proves what your users actually did, so your budget goes to the right people.
With Verify, you can run Verified User Acquisition with confidence, keeping people coming back with
retention tools like loyalty rewards, quests and achievements, and even power AI training and
evaluation using trusted, verified user groups, ensuring your models learn from clean data.
And when it's time to reward your community, there's the K-Store, a global rewards marketplace where
users can redeem perks that connect directly back to your app. Put simply, when growth is built on
real users, you grow faster. And that's exactly what Verify delivers. If you're building a web3,
AI, or gaming, request a demo to grow your protocol at www.kgen.io/demo. That's www.k-g-e-n.io/demo.
Okay, so Charles, this is a really good context in history. So basically, you're arguing that
banks, particularly a form of bank that you're talking about when you use the word bank, are
chartered banks, and they're really products of the nation state. And you don't really get a
modern nation state without a bank to accept that all nation states, some may or may not have armies
even, but they all have some sort of chartered bank function. Using this term chartered bank,
is that effectively a license that the state provides? It's basically regulation and it will give you
it's almost like a taxi cab medallion, let's say, if you operate a taxi cab in New York,
you have to have this medallion. Is that what a charter actually is?
In some literal sort of strict and narrow sense, the answer is yes, but to answer that way is
misses a big point. A chartered bank is the outcome of a bargain. That's the more interesting thing.
A chartered bank is something that's the outcome of what Steve Abraham and I call the game of bank
bargains. So there's always a coalition, whether it's an autocratic regime or democratic regime,
populist versus liberal democracy, different kinds of regimes that are going to strike a bargain.
There's going to be a coalition formed coming out of the power of the individual entities within
that nation. It's going to decide what they want to achieve with a bank charter. And the bank charter
is the answer to that question. It's not just a license. It defines the powers of the entity
and the limitations on those powers. It also defines things like what will happen when
the entity can't fulfill a contract. Does it get bailed out or not? Some of those
contracting provisions are explicit. Some of them are implicit. So if you really want to understand
what's going on, you don't just look at the letter of the law. And of course, a bank has to function
under the law. And so if it writes contracts, those contracts are only going to be as good as the
legal system, which is another political outcome. So the nation state is going to create laws
governing creditors' rights and debtors' rights generally. But it's also going to create as part
of the licensing of the banks. Limitations on powers, opportunities for powers for the bank,
and then also policies that are either explicit or implicit about bailing out that call that a
loss-sharing arrangement. So the bank is set up with a certain explicit or implicit loss-sharing
arrangements, like all chartered entities. It's so helpful when you're starting to think about this
to go back to 1600 when this whole idea was created. Because then you remember that chartered
corporations were special privileged corporations created by the state. At that time, special
corporations, not general incorporation acts, can allow anyone to apply to be one, special
corporations. And our own revolution is caught up in some of that and also caught up in some of
the loss-sharing arrangements. So let me just take us a little bit out in the weeds for a minute.
What was the Boston Tea Party about? And I'll bet you you'll get it wrong. What was it about Ryan?
I'll give you this civic answer, which is taxation without representation, right?
Completely wrong. That's what the Stamp Act Congress was about in 1765. And some of that
still fed into some thinking about the revolution. But the Boston Tea Party was about special
monopoly privilege that the East India Company was given because it had fallen on hard times.
It was suffering losses. And so the Crown and Parliament decided to change the Navigation Acts,
which were acts governing transport in the British Empire, to give a special privilege. I won't go
into the details, to give a special privilege to the East India Company for transporting tea,
which ended up having the effect of sidelining the New England merchants who were acting in
trafficking the tea. It cut the price of tea dramatically at my recollection is about half.
Why did the Boston merchants, why did people in Boston, do this what I think is a reprehensible
thing, by the way? Most of our founders found it reprehensible, except the people in Boston.
The other founders found it reprehensible. Why? Because they were really just
acting in a way that preserved their own interest and acting contrary to the well understood principle
that the sovereign England got to choose international rights and privileges as part
of its sovereign power. And it granted special privileges to the East India Company. And when
the East India Company fell into trouble, they tried to help it by changing the menu of privileges.
It disadvantaged some people, but it was not viewed by most people in our country at the time
as some kind of terrible action by the Crown. It was just part of the Navigation Acts system,
part of mercantilism, imperialism. And if you weren't one of those merchants in Boston,
like the Adamses, by the way, you didn't have a big problem with it. What you did have a problem
with was the Stamp Act, which was in 1765. Tried to say that for the first time, the Parliament
was going to impose taxes on local domestic transactions, which should be under the purview
of the legislatures in the colonies, because it's the colonies had their own legislatures.
That was unprincipled. That was a violation of the rights of British citizens. And that's why
we didn't like it in 1765. The reason I illustrate our discussion with that example is not to just
highlight the widespread ignorance that Americans have about our own history, like the American
Revolution. The Boston Tea Party was not popular outside of New England and was viewed as unprincipled
and wrong by most of our leaders, but that's not the way we learn it. But the more important
thing is to understand the whole system that was taken for granted of the management of
the interests of the nation state had to do with creating charters, both for corporations and for
banks, which were corporations, to try to be a kind of representation of and a way of executing
the interests of the sovereign. And that wasn't viewed as somehow wrong. So the notion of general
incorporation, the notion that you, Ryan, have the right to form a corporation, to act as an
abstract entity to engage in transactions and maybe have stockholders in that corporation and
maybe even have limited liability in that corporation. The notion that that's going to happen as a
matter of general right, what's called general incorporation laws, and also along the other side
of that, there were not going to do specially privileged corporations. That was not something
that became part of the American way of thinking until the 1840s. So what happened with banks
to get back to them is, of course, they started off being specially privileged entities,
just like the East India Company, chartered by the national government or by the states.
And it wasn't until the 1830s in some states that we had general incorporation laws governing
banks, giving anyone the opportunity to charter one under pre-specified rules. And then, of course,
we have the national banking system created by Lincoln in the 1860s and 1863, which then created
a national government set of charters. Again, licenses, as you said, but not just licenses,
just like the East India Company, there are deals explicit or implicit about how losses
are going to be allocated. And the reason I mention that is because you can't understand the modern
state of the 21st century without understanding the way that bank charters effectively create
loss sharing arrangements that are bailing out banks, and that those are all about imposing
losses on others to subsidize banks. So once you understand that banks have always served
from the very beginning, the interests of the state and are the result of the political game
of bank bargains, then you really have some insight and you understand it's not just about
their license, but it's about who supports them, who creates them, who will bail them out.
And that's all part of the political gain that creates banks. And I know we've spent some time
for taking time on this, but I want to emphasize, you can't have a prayer of understanding what the
future stablecoins is without coming to grips with this fact. If you think stablecoins are
technologically determined, the future stablecoins is something that comes from my fantasies about
the economic logic and empirical evidence of what works and doesn't work, you're really missing
the boat. Stablecoins have to be if they're going to work, they have to work within that
coalition building game of bank bargains. And we've already seen in the Genius Act,
the way that that coalition tried to shape the way stablecoins would or wouldn't happen.
And Ryan, the most important fact is, four years ago, the Biden administration
wanted to kill this idea as best they could. And in fact, even before them, the first Trump
administration, which I served as chief economist at the OCC with Brian Brooks as the acting
controller, the Trump administration didn't want this to happen either. They've changed they've
changed their tune. And so when Brian Brooks and I, I'm now going to tell tales out of school here,
Brian Brooks and I were very eager to see the crypto future realized, the stablecoins realized
that we recognized that would have to happen by chartering entities that were allowed to do
stablecoin transactions. There are a lot of advantages to come from that. And of course,
what's the administration in US history? The only one that since 1863 that did not actually
appoint a comptroller of the currency confirmed by the Senate. The answer is the Biden administration.
Why? Because they wanted it to do nothing. They wanted the OCC to be a complete nothing,
to not do anything, to go down the road that Brian Brooks and Jonathan Gould and others at the OCC
and I had hoped to start, which was bringing into the game of bank bargains a formal crypto presence
so that it could actually occur as a legitimized financial transaction that would have real legs.
The Biden administration, completely captured by the incumbent banks and by other political
interests, they're part of a coalition of the status quo, did not yet that to happen. The Trump
administration this time wants it to happen the first time it didn't. Can you explain that a little
bit further Charles? Yeah, but I just want to point out, what am I really getting at? What I'm
getting at is what we've already experienced. If we understand what we just lived through for the
past eight years, what we just experienced is how much the political wins have affected the timing
and capabilities of the empowerment of crypto. If you think crypto is happening now because of
some exogenous technologically driven reality, you really are just completely hopeless, because
the technology has been there all along. It's been there for, and that's going to matter for
what we're talking about today because I'm going to point out the technology that exists today
will predictably, completely transform, can predictably, completely transform financial
transactions. But the main obstacle to getting that to happen is the resistance that's coming from
members of powerful coalitions who have vested interest contrary to that. The incumbent banks
finally saw that they were not going to be protected enough, so they needed to get
that's what happened in the Genius Act. They needed to get the ability to make chartering
the way that stable coins could happen. Notice you can't run stable coins without a charter now.
That's what the Genius Act did. The Genius Act, but notice that the incumbents changed their
political strategy. Pay attention listeners pay attention. The incumbents changed their political
strategy from ignoring stable coins and having Biden's report say, "Oh, risky, risky, risky, risky."
But still allowing them, they didn't have the power to stop them legislatively. They didn't
have the coalition built to stop them. They just threw a lot of sand at them, said they were risky,
risky, risky, and definitely didn't want to follow up on what Brian Brooks and his team,
including me, had been trying to do, which is bring them into the modern chartering of the banking
system, legitimize them, allow them to be regulated, but regulated in a way that gave them a future.
Well, the incumbent banks didn't want that to happen. They were very happy with the Biden
administration's approach, but then as things started to change and they realized there would
be an inevitable growth of stable coins, which have grown dramatically over the past five years.
Then what did they do? They said, "Well, we have to somehow try to limit stable coins
and allow them to be part of the chartered entity." I don't think that's ultimately a crippling
limit. In fact, I think it's very helpful for stable coins to be part of chartered reality,
especially if we have other ways for stable coins to exist. For example,
they don't have to be just chartered by the national banking system. They could be chartered
by the individual states or different ways. There's competition. Anyway, I think that it's a very
positive step, but I really think you can't understand this as a technological phenomenon.
Only. It is a technological phenomenon. But notice, the Federal Reserve is extremely threatened by
stable coins, because stable coins can create a payment system network that completely sidesteps
Fedwire. Eventually, it's so much better that it has to beat the Fed. The Fed doesn't just
sit in there passively. What are they trying to do? Let's create central bank digital currency.
It's going to be so great. Then what was the Biden administration's view? They didn't beat
up central bank digital currency. They knew it wasn't very popular, so they didn't push it too hard.
But then they completely just threw sand at stable coins so that what are the incumbent banks
doing? They're part of that same coalition. By the way, there are a lot of other community
and other activists organizations that have benefited from their partnerships with the chartered
incumbents, the big banks, which became big banks very recently in US history in the 1990s
in the 2000s. We didn't have big banks prior to that. That was the merger wave. When we got those
big banks, the way they got big was to avoid political opposition from activist organizations.
They gave the activist organizations money in order to testify for them in support of their
mergers. I bet your listeners don't know that either. Do you know how much activist organizations
were granted contractually for merging banks from 1995 to 2007? Take a guess, Ryan. Total
contractual, these are explicit financial contracts. You, Ryan, come testify at the Federal Reserve
Board to say, I'm a good guy. That's it. I'm a good guy, and my merger should be approved.
And if you do that, I'm going to give you a contract that gives you some money.
Some of that money is to pass through to your friends as subsidized loans. Some of that money
is outright grant to you, 10% of it. How much do you think changed hands? When you when you
want to understand the politics of what charters need, this is crucial. The entire creation of the
big banking system since the 1990s was the result of a bargain among several parties. But in fact,
a lot of those parties were community activist organizations.
So let's just get your listeners to learn something. What's the total dollar amount of those contracts
over the period 1995 to 2007? What do you think? Let's be clear. These are contracts between who?
Merging banks. Let's say Bank of America is going to merge with a bank where, let's say,
when fleet and Bank Boston merged in 1999, I think it was, they entered into contracts with
local activist groups. So this is what's a local activist group? Think Jesse Jackson.
Oh, okay. Interesting. Yeah. So how much did those groups get either to keep for themselves 10% or
90% of it to pass through to their members? By the way, how do you get to be a member of the group?
Show up for a political protest, then you get access to a subsidized mortgage.
You understand now how political coalitions are built? I see.
So how much money are we talking about? I'm going to guess tens of millions,
because it was a more innocent time in the billions, I think, for something like this.
No, from 1995 to 2007, two and a half trillion dollars of contracts.
Wait, what trillion? Two and a half trillion.
That's what you guys don't know. That's why you don't get it, right? That's why nobody gets
kicked. Can I, let's talk to all the money. Yeah. I mean, that's, I guess, the total value of
the contracts, you know, I mean, because I guess various stakeholders would skim off the top in
various ways. I actually think, Charles, so a few things that you're communicating to us,
bankless listeners, that that's important is that stablecoins in particular aren't just a technology.
Of course, they're not. They're a political banking mechanism. It's always infused together.
I actually do think that crypto has somewhat learned this a little bit in the small
over the last couple of years, because crypto has become incredibly politically engaged and
evolved. I think in no small part that led to the passage of the Genius Act, if you look at kind
of the political crypto fintech lobbying that the industry has done over the past couple of years,
I mean, it's been spectacular. There's been a lot of money pouring into kind of the political
games in order to get this legislation through. So we're starting to learn those lessons,
but I appreciate you actually, right? It's not easy. I'm not trying to be a jerk, right? I'm just
trying to tell people that they're stupid, not that or ignorant, but I am telling people that they,
that it's not easy. And the reason it's not easy is, so first of all, if you don't understand the
political equilibrium, then you can't oppose it. You can't change it. You can't, you can't try to
build your own group. And yes, they have started to build their own group. But the point is,
these things exist within a legal framework, within an engineering framework, and within an
economic framework. What I found when I was involved in crypto is, those are three different minds,
and they rarely come together. And then that's too limited, because then there's the political
framework that allows the bringing together of these three minds. And so what I found when I was
working in crypto is there are people who know one of the three ways of thinking, engineering,
economics, or legal, at very, very few who understand the combination, and almost none who understand
the political contingency of actually being able to succeed. And I hope we're going to talk about
the distant future, because I think crypto, but especially stablecoins, everyone understands that
they have extraordinary promise as a medium of exchange. But I want to go a lot farther and point
out that the amazing thing about the blockchain, distributed ledger technology, is that it can
allow not just the best medium exchange system the world has ever seen, but it can also allow the
best unit of account system. It can basically create a substitute, or I wouldn't say substitute,
let's just say a new definition of the dollar. And of course, when you start thinking that way,
now we're talking about not only replacing all the incumbent banks and all their entrenched
allies who have gotten so much money from them, but also the Federal Reserve. And let's remember
that chartered central banks, which work called central banks, they were called banks of issue
when they were chartered in the 1600s, but central banks like the Fed, which are really
something that's only been around and called the central bank since about the middle of the 19th
century. They're very young. They're not likely to be a permanent feature of our economy. In fact,
my own work suggests that this is a technology that's really it's time to get rid of it.
And they're not going to go easily, right? Those people aren't going to go easily.
Before we get into the far future of what this technology is capable of, let's talk
about the here and now. So we have the genius bill signed, of course. You have a presentation
talking about the stablecoins are here and they're going to transform banking. Seems like you're
making the case that they're going to unbundle some of the services that banks offer today.
What pieces are stablecoins going to unbundle from the banks? I mean, there has to be a reason
that the existing incumbent banks are threatened by this that no progress was made during the Biden
administration that they've thrown sand in the gears at every corner. Why? What are they scared
of? What's going to be unbundled? What do they lose? Great, great question. Okay, so first, a
confession. I made my reputation largely off of the theory of bundling of bank services.
My most cited article is a theory article that explains, and there's another theory
article using slightly different logic that explains why banks do and have historically
bundled payment services with lending services. Why do banks lend and clear payments? Why do
they do both? Because there are entities historically that have done just one or the other.
For example, the world's most successful intermediary of the early 17th century was something called
the Riesel Bank, the Bank of Amsterdam, it's also called, and it was initially entirely about
clearing bills of exchange in international merchant commerce. But then I mentioned,
sort of merchant banks, the Medici, the Rothschilds, they weren't operating clearing systems. They were
lenders. So banks can do one or the other, but if you look at chartered banks, what you realize is
the history of chartered banks has been the combining of payment system services with lending.
So we as economists have developed a few different theories about this. I'm happy to go into the
weeds on it. But the theories really have to do with some kind of mechanism design advantage,
generally related to some kind of information cost or information problem that encourages banks
to do both so that the competitive equilibrium isn't that banks do one or the other because it's
more efficient to do them together. Now, that idea has a lot of empirical evidence behind it and
a lot of theory. But let me just point out, because it's grounded in a theory of information cost,
it's contingent. The idea that bundling is efficient depends on some kind of information cost argument.
If one of the things that modern information technology is doing is changing the cost of
information and reducing the cost to, if that's happening, it might undermine the logic that
creates bundling. That's exactly what I believe, that bundling made economic sense for banks and no
longer does. And bundling specifically, Charles, you're talking about the bank's existing business
model is to bundle both what you're calling payments and also lending those two together.
And I think when you say payments, you also mean basically the checking account. So deposits,
is that correct? Yeah, that's the mechanism in the US that we're using for making transactions
through Fedwire. So it's all this centralized payment system operating through the central bank.
You might think, and your listeners, I think, well, wait a minute, I use PayPal or I use Venmo
or something, all you're doing is going, that's just stuff up here. It still is all going through
the centralized payment system of deposit checking accounts at banks that work with each other through
Fedwire typically, or other ways. If stablecoins take off and the way I think you predict,
maybe Secretary Scott Besson predicts, certainly we predict at bank lists, right?
The checking account and payments, that becomes unbundled from the bank services.
So your checking account is basically as a individual, in a US society, becomes basically
a stablecoin account. And the banks are just left with lending. And they don't like that very much,
because I've got to assume they make a lot of money on the checking and payment side things.
Is this simple as that? Not quite, but yes, I mean, you've got it, but let me just complicate it a
little. Let me point out that there are shadow banks, not just chartered banks,
shattered banks that specialize in lending, just as their shadow banks or shadow payment
services to specialize just in payments. So yeah, the shadow payment provider is tethered.
They have more than 90% of the market in stablecoins. But then there are all these
lending services that are done online. They don't fund themselves with deposits, and they're not
connected to stablecoins. So the first thing for us to notice is in the shadow banking area,
where only market competition and efficiency governs the structure of the intermediaries.
What have they chosen to do? They specialize. They don't combine services.
They're not doing lending and stablecoins. They're doing lending or stablecoins.
I think that makes perfect sense. And in my articles recently, I've talked about why
unbundling is so illuminating. So when you look at the shadow, you're seeing that the modern solutions
are unbundling. Now, that's partly because if you're a shadow bank, it's very hard to do.
You can't be involved in the checking system. But there's more to it than that, because people
aren't choosing tethered, is finding itself strongly driven toward what? Trying to create
a kind of payment system without a lot of risk on the asset side. So that is very important
that whatever those old bundling advantages were, I would argue that they've been undermined by
improvements in information technology that no longer require these two things or are benefited
from doing these two things together. That's a complicated and fairly deep economic argument.
But I think people can get the basic gist of the job. What we're talking about is look at the
shadow banks that you see. Stablecoin providers aren't trying to do lending. Lending providers
aren't trying to do stablecoins. That's very interesting, because if there were big synergies,
as there have been in the past between combining the two, they would be trying to do both, but they
don't. So the future, I think, is now coming back to your statement, which I agree with.
The future is that they can come and bank see that they no longer are going to have this
basically chartered bank subsidy of having this kind of oligopolistic control of a deposit-based
system that then funds and subsidizes their lending activities. That is not a permanent
feature of our financial system, but it's not going to go away easily. It's because the banks
have huge power by virtue of their political influences. They are extremely powerful organizations,
and they even operate through the organization that today is the most evil organization in the
United States. I wonder if you've ever even heard of it. I'll guess your listeners have it. It's
called the Bank Policy Institute. It sounds so objective. It sounds so scholarly. It sounds so
wonderful that someone who is out there doing the public good of talking about bank policy,
no, no, no, no. It's Darth Vader on steroids, okay? Darth Vader on steroids. This group is
not just about colluding, not just the biggest banks colluding, but using their power to try to
stop things that will help citizens in favor of themselves, and they're really evil. I can tell
you, when I was chief economist at the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency, I would read
their statements whenever we had a regulation. They were the most excreable things I ever read.
The idea that an economist working for the Bank Policy Institute could write such things,
must be so alienating for them, and so miserable their existence that I don't see how they can
stand it. But that's what power is all about. These aren't just operating individually. They're
operating collectively through this collective action entity, and if funnels, it sponsors conferences
at universities, like where I used to be Columbia University, and controls professors through the
money that it provides for sponsoring those conferences. You kind of understand politics to
understand banking. Charles, one thing we want to explore is on the same thread. Ryan and I,
and probably the vast majority of our listeners anecdotally, understand the trend shift about
where money and banking is going. Ryan and I use Ethereum as our banking layer. I write a monthly
check to my landlord because that's the only way I can pay him money, and that is the only activity
that is left in my Wells Fargo account is like my monthly rent payment. And over time, as this
bankless thing that we have tried to encourage evolves and becomes more mature, I think that's
probably true for just a larger and larger percentage of the population. Our banking activity is done
in our Ethereum wallets on stable coins, and it's coming at a loss to our account activity in Wells
Fargo, our deposit base in Wells Fargo. And that's because of the hundreds of billions of dollars
that are now available on Ethereum. Now, is the bank policy institute that you just named as Darth
Vader, which I'm a huge fan of. I don't, I would like to learn more about that, but I'm already a
fan of calling it Darth Vader. Is that what we are up against? Is that what we are doing?
They're coordinating entity just as, and I'm not trying to be partisan here, the Democratic
National Committee is another coordinating entity. The Democrat Party is all in on this.
A lot of the Republican Party is too, but the Republican Party isn't in agreement against this
future, as we can see now. And in fact, you even saw the Genius Act had bipartisan support. So
you're seeing cracks in the coalition. That's what's so interesting. This coalition that had
decided not to even appoint an office, an OCC comptroller, they had decided to just block all the
progress Brian Brooks had tried to do. All of a sudden, now we have legislation allowing this
with bipartisan support from this Congress that can't even agree on what day of the week it is.
That's pretty interesting. That tells you that there's been a political shift and it's worth
analysis that I don't claim to be fully understanding every aspect of that.
But that's where we need to go. And of course, you're right that you're seeing that with Ethereum.
And by the way, my understanding is, I think you said it, that you have your stablecoins
in a wallet on Ethereum. And you can also, my understanding is Tether can be both
in Ethereum and in Bitcoin. You could either put it on the platform
of an exchange or you can put it within the blockchain. And I think that's really interesting.
So yeah, that's where we're going. We have, of course, we have a long way to go, because as you
pointed out, you still pay your landlord with a chat, right? So we have to get it so that you can
buy coffee off your cell phone with stablecoins. And that means that we have to create a decentralized
network for stablecoin retail transactions. So it's not just about buying and selling crypto
mainly using Tether mainly for crypto transactions, but using them in the real world.
But this is easy. This is just creating a little box on retail, just as they have credit cards,
where they're doing it with stablecoins. The technology is already there. In fact,
this technology is already there, not just to completely sidestep the bank incumbent payment
system with stablecoins, but to actually change even, I know this is very futuristic. We'll get
to it to supplant the dollar to create a new concept of transacting a new unit of account.
But I want to emphasize that can't happen without politics. Under article one,
section eight of our Constitution, Congress has the power to determine, to control the money.
And they have used that power and interpreted that very much as their own right to decide what
a legal tender is. That means something that can actually be used as a payment mechanism
legally to satisfy debts. If Congress doesn't want the new unit of account to happen,
that I have in mind, creating this new synthetic dollar out of the blockchain
to and get rid of the Federal Reserve dollar, then it doesn't have to happen. So until the
politics, what we see with the Genius Act is the beginning of the cracks in the anti-stablecoin
coalition. Now we have a bipartisan agreement to have to make chartered, to allow chartered banks
to do stablecoins. By the way, this is huge because when I was at the OCC, I can tell you
the one thing the OCC has done right for the last 160 years has been examining as a credible third
party. So you want stablecoin issuers, because let me tell you something, a lot of your listeners
aren't going to like it. I think tether is kind of sleazy. They have been, right? They're kind of,
let's just use the word that your generation likes, sketchy. They're sketchy, right? They are
little sketchy. Imagine now instead, you've got some boring bureaucrat who's paid just to
examine the algorithm, make sure that the algorithm is what the stablecoin provider says it is,
and examine the reserve balance held at some fiduciary, and make sure that it is what they say it is.
And that examination is pretty much the entire role that we need the regulator to do.
And what we really need is for the regulator to somehow commit, not to let the political
compromises of the future lead it to try to control stablecoins. And that's tricky,
because I'm not telling you I've got the magic bullet for that, so the Genius Act cuts both
ways, right? Once you stay stablecoins have to be part of a chartered entity, you open up the
possibility that that thing can be regulated to start giving subsidies to Jesse Jackson,
just like our chartered banking system decided to do in the 1990s.
So it's all politically contingent. So if you guys think that because we are forward-looking
people who like technology and want to see good technologies happen, that they will automatically
happen. It's not true. You have to be a political force to build a coalition that represents the
public's interest. If the public isn't informed, like you guys weren't informed that two and a half
trillion dollars had been contracted from merging banks to these optimist local activist organizations,
that's why they succeed, right? So the political coalition doesn't always represent the common
interests of the public. In fact, it almost never does. So this is where the real problems are.
We can talk about how, yes, of course, we can circumvent this whole centralized payment system
run by the Fed, and we can have it immediately, a medium of exchange done more securely,
more quickly, in ways that allow you to combine messaging with payments. So you can enrich the
whole process of the payment system. All of that can happen at the speed of light in a decentralized
network that can't be hacked, unlike Fedwire, which will definitely be hacked. All of this is true.
However, it's all contingent. And then going beyond that, to use the data that's in the blockchain
in some kind of anonymized way to create information about what the consumption bundles are,
so that you can then construct a new unit of account that's more optimally configured than
the dollar is using economic theory that we've had for 150 years. So yes, that can happen,
but not if Congress decides that that definition of the dollar won't be a legal tender.
So we have to get mobilized to educate ourselves and to therefore exert the power on politicians.
So you're going to have to create organized groups. There's no such thing as decentralized
political activity. You have to create organized groups to promote this future.
Imagine a world where traditional finance meets the power of blockchain seamlessly. That's
what mantle is pioneering with blockchain for banking, a revolutionary new category at the
intersection of tradfi and web3. At the heart is you are the world's first money app built fully
on chain. It gives you a Swiss I ban account blending fiat currencies like the euro, the Swiss
fronk, the United States dollar or the rimimbi with crypto all in one place. Enjoy real world
usability and blockchains trust and program ability. Transactions post directly to the blockchain
compatible with tradfi rails and packed with integrated DeFi futures. You are transforms
mantle network into the ultimate platform for on chain financial services, unifying payments,
trading and assets like the MI for the ME protocol and functions FBTC backed by developer grants,
ecosystem incentives and top distribution through the you are app reward stations and buy bit launch
pool for mnt holders. Every economic activity in you are drives value back to you embodying the
entire stack and future growth of this super app ecosystem. Follow mantle on X at mantle underscore
official for the latest updates on blockchain for banking. That's x.com slash mantle underscore
official. Degen started as a tight knit community on farcaster and organically grew into one of the
top meme coins on base. What began as a simple idea tip anyone who joins the fun sparked an economy
that turned into a movement. The community runs the show from the logo and the lower
to funding and building ambitious ideas together. Over 1 million dee gens now power each other with
their generosity, creativity and ability to get things done at the center is the dee gen token.
It rewards engagement, fuels tipping and drives the marketplace for builders and fans. That same
energy gave rise to dee gen chain a fast low cost layer three for new projects and now the dee gen
app the easiest way to connect, earn and participate in decentralized social media with a built in
wallet and real token utility in dee gen the hat stays on join dee gen and get on the app
wait list at www dot dee gen dot tips. When you research a new protocol you shouldn't have to
juggle 12 tabs just to get the full picture market data on chain activity, social sentiment,
developer updates. They're all scattered across different platforms surf brings it all together.
It's the first crypto AI platform that combines institution grade research with on train execution
in one interface from discovery and research to action surf gives you a full end to end experience
instead of bouncing between dune defi llama twitter and github surf gives you the story behind the
data in seconds. Whether you're evaluating a protocol tracking positions monitoring whale
moves or exploring the next narrative surf upgrades your workflow so you can spend less time piecing
things together and more time making informed decisions check out surf today and experience
crypto AI that actually works sign up now and use code bank list to get a seven day free trial to
surf pro click the link in the description for more information. I want to get your take on a
current political battle that is happening right now on the back of the genius act. I'm gonna throw
some things out there just to set the landscape and then let you know allow you to comment on it so
this is on the element of yield from stablecoins. Okay and so it's an active issue right now so the
genius bill prohibits issuers so when it do you like tether or circle for USCC from actually
providing yield to their consumers however there is a loophole let's call it which means any other
yeah any other entity uh sort of in the value flow can actually provide that interest from
treasuries back to the stablecoin recipient you know like in the form of rewards so for instance
you keep your USDC on coinbase and you actually get the four percent from treasuries and a bank
doesn't get that okay so this is an active fight right now I actually read I don't know if you've
seen this but there was a article in Brookings uh from uh Aaron Klein this week okay and I don't know
if this is the influence of the the BPI and Darth Vader sure or if Aaron Klein is a huge defender
of the status okay let me let me give you what he says and then I want you to poke like tell me
what you think about it what stands up from an economist perspective he basically says rewards
our dangerous loophole he says uh it's be you know if you look at what happened to money market funds
okay so money market funds through history 2008 etc had to be bailed out by the government and he's
saying the same is going to happen to stablecoins he also highlights the deposit flight concerns
basically it's going to bleed bank deposits checking accounts dry that is going to hurt
lending and financial uh stability for the entire banking system so he says you know congress should
actually go back to the genius bill and close the loophole make it such that consumers individual
citizens the stablecoins do not get that interest under any circumstances and he argues it's pivotal
so so Ryan I mean you've you've mentioned four fallacious things in a sequence so you have to
get a little slower and let me point out why each of them is fallacious all right let's take them
all take them all okay so first of all money market funds bailouts were not economically
inevitable they were a political outcome so to say that the fact that money markets were bailed
out when they broke the buck was somehow had to be true is is wrong um if if instead the government
hadn't bailed them out the world would just be fine okay so so then now let's give him a little
bit of a credit and say well what he's saying is that the rail politic will be that stablecoins
will that path of least resistance will lead to bailing out of stablecoins when they have losses
okay so I don't believe that's true either because one of the things that we can do with stablecoins
is we can require them to have automatic resetting algorithms so that if they suffer a loss
now we have a couple of alternatives one is to restrict what the assets can be so they only hold
short-term debt treasury debt as assets in which case there's no real possibility of loss
or we can allow them to have a broader set of assets but then to have an automatic reset algorithm
that then when there's a loss in assets has an automatic thing happen in the stablecoins
so people when they buy stablecoins know exactly what they're getting into
my own view would be to allow both to allow both the riskless stablecoins and the risky stablecoins
with the reset and I think that my understanding of political economy which is fairly deep is that
if it's done that way there won't be bailouts with stablecoins so that the notion of stablecoins
will be risky if no that's not true if they're examined and if they have either the algorithmic
adjustments with full transparency or or if you don't believe in that you could you could say
well and I want to initially restrict them to only hold treasury bills again chartered and monitored
I can understand that that argument makes sense but no he's wrong of course this is what the
advocates of the incumbents are all about doing whether they're BPI or Aaron Klein what they're
really about doing is they operate in organizations who pay their salaries to make up arguments like
this so I'm sorry go ahead tell me more I just wanted to get into that that's great so that's
the first one let's get into the deposit flight concern okay so it's gonna bleed the bank deposits
dry and that's gonna go first of all well of course no no the deposits banks should in equilibrium
because there's no longer an advantage from bundling the equilibrium should be that banks
raise their money their money from outside market sources so you can think of it as securitization
which is a well-known banking source of funding or outright debt issues by banks that aren't part
of the transacting medium why shouldn't banks do that finance companies do it
finance companies have been doing since the 1960s maybe because it's harder they don't like it and
Aaron knows they're paying his salary including believe me they are believe me they are can I
know Aaron he's a nice guy but I know where his salary comes from I know where Brookings I know
what Brookings is all about okay and so so yeah of course they don't like it they don't like
competition they're gonna fight it and they're gonna hire people at the BPI or the Aaron Klein's
of the world or they're gonna have politicians like Maxine Waters say risky risky risky risky
or Joe Biden creating his white paper from his little commission it's all risky risky risky no
it's not risky risky risky if it's designed properly and I think you know as a historian
and a theorist of bank runs I don't think there's anybody who knows them as well as I do that just
doesn't have to be the equilibrium let me also point out stablecoins should not be debt obligations
in my opinion they should not be constructed as debt obligations they should it's so in my papers
about this I pointed out why not take advantage of it some existing law and make them perpetual
preferred stock so I know that this isn't necessarily the way people are all thinking but if it's
perpetual preferred stock then notice you could have dividends in principle and I'll come back to
your question on that because of course when I asked the person at circle before they announced
their IPO how they were going to deal with the Genius Act the answer was you can create a securities
rap for owning the stablecoins and the securities rap can pay interest think of it as perpetual
preferred stock so perpetual preferred stock never has a maturity date if you don't pay the coupon
you're not in default you don't go into bankruptcy so you could have an algorithmic readjustment if
there were a problem but think about perpetual preferred stock with a dividend that actually
owns the stablecoin so that you when you buy the stablecoin you also buy preferred stock that
owns the stablecoin preferred stock pays you is a perpetual preferred stock that pays you a dividend
and let me tell you another reason this is so potentially advantageous if you ever heard of the
the global dollar network yes that's a that's a stablecoin as well right it's the Paxos behind
it's a joint venture yes it's a joint venture by Robin Hood um Anchorage and Paxos and but their
their vision is there are big economies of scale to having a single stablecoin but there are all
these economies of relationship of consumer relationships that mean that they need to partner with
Amazon Walmart you go down the list right why not let those individual entities who partner with
them bring who bring the relationships the consumer relationships to the stablecoin network why not
let them retain the customer relationship so you could imagine that you Ryan want to you want to
get global dollar network because it's it's going to build itself as a as a rail as a kind of
infrastructure of stablecoin to be able to compete with tether through high scale great I really think
they will and when they do that though when Walmart brings someone to that stablecoin Walmart maybe
could construct their own preferred perpetual preferred stock that owns the stable the global
dollar network stablecoins that are its customer relationship and it can decide the interest it
pays on that perpetual preferred stock yeah so of course you know that the only way you could have
gotten the incumbent banks to be part of this is to try to limit it and to to think but then
the other people in that political bargain had already figured out before the genius act was
passed the person at circle I talked to told me this that this was their strategy so it's kind of
like you know of course this is not going to work limiting the interest on stablecoins is so
stupid and it's so concrete it it shows you how the incumbents hate you they hate the the American
public they they have only contempt for us that they don't want any product they can compete for
our business to be able to pay us interest so that they can keep us how disgusting are these incumbent
banks wow Charles you might hate banks more than bankless does which is absolutely saying something
I think I know more about them than you know you do well again can I ask you a broader question if
this is fully realized let's say we win this political battle let's say it's inevitable let's
say basically what we talk about it in terms you you're talking about perpetual perpetual preferred
stocks we talk about that in terms of yield right it's like let's say the yield goes back to the
end customer my question is like here's something I don't understand so maybe put your monetary
economist hat on for this which is I don't understand then in that case why we actually need
dollars so here's what I sort of mean basically okay so if David and I and David was talking
about paying his landlord let's say he can pay his landlord with a stablecoin that's wrapped in
yield okay so we could totally do this from a technical perspective there could be some sort
of stablecoin that effectively gives David the fed fund rate of four percent then he gets that
as a dividend let's say all the intermediaries are pretty much cut out the margins are compressed
so that mostly David receives that he'd rather hold that four percent yield stablecoin thing
rather than dollars and so would everybody like on the planet everybody would rather use
the yield thing rather than dollars but doesn't this just cut dollars out of the equation everyone's
using these sort of you know treasury templates so not completely okay so so now this is really
important we have to distinguish the role of the dollars a medium of exchange from the role of the
dollars a unit of account notice tether and almost all stablecoins are denominated in dollars some
are denominated in euros and yen but more than 90 percent are denominated in dollars I think the
short term the growth of stablecoins will actually strengthen the role of the dollar in global markets
it'll allow people in countries to have really bad currencies to switch some of their liquid
balances to dollar denominated counts so the first thing to note is the short-term effect
of using stablecoins as a medium in exchange will actually be probably to strengthen the
role of the dollar as a unit of account there are only a couple trillion of these actual physical
dollars that are being handed back and forth mainly by criminals I have some in my wallet too
I'm not a criminal but yeah but mainly by criminals so but the so the dollar doesn't serve a very
big function right now as a medium of exchange in physical dollars but then there are other dollars
that are called reserves the banks hold that are basically what is the backing thing the sort of
small piece that allows deposits to work so that's another medium of exchange so the federal reserve
not only creates it creates two media of exchange effectively one or reserves the other is dollars
and that's a medium of exchange use but it also the dollar as a valuable thing that's exchanged
in the market that has a value relative to your commodities and services and other currencies
that's a valuable unit of account stablecoins are denominated in dollars so the dollar doesn't
disappear just because stablecoins displace deposits and currency as medium of exchange
because the dollar still retains its role as a unit of account but it doesn't have to why
because what is a unit of account unit of account it's just how we denominate all of our transactions
we could decide to create so let me let me give an example suppose that we lived
we all of us lived in Champaignar Battle and Champaignar Battle pretty much the whole
local economy other than the university is soybean and corn that's what's produced there
and in fact even the stores that sell other things you know if soybeans and corn's do badly
they do badly right so think of it for a minute like let's get rid of soybeans it's just corn
they grow corn and eat corn let's say it's a really simple life that's all there is to it
all that we do in this one location is we grow corn and eat corn and when we work we we work
to grow corn so when we work should we be paid in dollars should we denominate wages
in dollars should we denominate prices and dollars wouldn't it be just simpler
yes the answer is yes if we just pay people in units of corn and we denominate everything in
corn because there's only one commodity called corn why should you if you lived in Champaignar
Battle you wouldn't want to if if if you were only eating corn i'm not saying that's true of
people in Champaignar Battle but suppose it were then they wouldn't want to denominate things in
dollars they just denominate them in corn they'd be paid in corn and they'd eat corn they grow corn
eat corn get paid in corn that's it you wouldn't need a dollar new marina okay now let me generalize
that point Jevins one of the great founders of modern economics in the late 19th and early 20th
century developed the theory of the unit of account and what an optimal unit of account is
and basically showed us something very intuitive which is the optimal unit of account that we want
to be paid in would be our consumption bundle because then if we know so if you consume 10
different things in certain ways you'd really like your your payment to be denominated in that
because then when you get paid you know you you get you know in advance you're going to get a
certain amount of consumption so your your pay contract translates directly into your consumption
and that means that when the there's no like slippage coming from variation in the value of your
payment relative to your consumption preference right so that's what Jevins realized now here's
the amazing miraculous thing blockchain records and allows you to extract in an anonymized way
what the consumption bundle is once it becomes a network in which services and commodities
are all transacted through the blockchain we actually we actually can know in a particular
location what the consumption bundle is so we can get a lot closer to an optimal unit of account
and we could even now it gets really interesting maybe some locations will have their own specialized
unit of account so we don't just have one unit of account but we have subunits of account now they'd
be aggregated to to create the national dollar that would be trading with other economies but that
they could have separate units of account so that people could have their own value of the sort of
New England dollar and the southeastern dollar and the western dollar and and then allowing those to
all be legal tender and then having a national dollar that's a weighted aggregation of that
would allow us to all be paid in ways that would be much more optimal for us as a as from the
perspective of consumers is this really practical the answer is yes because blockchain allows the
recording of all that information in perpetuity which we know we can access in an anonymized way
it's not trivial but the technology already exists to do that selective anonymity is what
it's sometimes called in blockchain transactions and so yeah of course you can do that physically
it's not not a problem but then will will the political game of bank bargains allow it how do we
get that to happen the other thing that's a important wrinkle of that is to actually transact in
something that that's this sort of basket you're going to need reserves that the different stable
coin issuers transact with each other basically bundle of the consumption good and how do you do
that well you have um believe it or not you would have um not everyone but some finite group you
denominate the bundle let's say as um a stake from roots Chris steakhouse a filet mignon from
roots Chris steakhouse it's less um a bag of Lay's potato chips both sold by particular sellers
okay and then those so how do those sellers create a reserve bundle that combines the two
they issue instead of um issuing these little cards that allow you to buy you know at roots
Chris you issue a filet mignon IOU so the really interesting idea is to tokenize
um IOUs that are linked to specific commodities provided by or services provided by particular
local firms this sounds really far out but actually technologically it's trivial the the tricky thing
is to actually create how somebody comes up with what the optimal bundle should be and in my papers
I talk about the different trade-offs there it's going to be there's going to be a trade-off where
you want to have some you don't want everyone in the economy to be producing these tokenized
reserves but you do want it to be a small member who kind of span the consumption bundle reasonably
well but who have very low default risk we're going to have to have algorithms about what to do with
the tokens when you want to go to roots Chris to redeem your filet mignon but they're out of business
so we're going to have to there's a fair amount of algorithmic kind of um complexity to creating
these reserves but the the promise of it the reason it's worth doing is that it will create
so much better outcome in terms of making the unit of account much closer to what we consume
so right now we have this compromise unit of account the dollar it's a one-size-fits-all
no matter what location you're in you you have to deal with it that there gonna be lots of other
issues like well should this whose consumption bundle should this be should it be kind of an
aggregation of the whole region that would be my preference but you can also imagine that there
this could be a political football where we use poor people's consumption bundle some people
advocate that because they think of it as it's it's a form of trying to subsidize or help the poor
so i just want to you know keep emphasizing all of these economic ideas have to be filtered
through the political system because politically congress decides what the legal tender is
and then finally just point out once we get this great system it's still contingent i mean
congress could decide to start taxing stablecoins congress could decide to require stablecoins
to give subsidies to particular targeted individuals but i think from the standpoint of
economic theory we can see clearly that getting rid of the federal reserve getting rid of the
incumbent banking system in terms of the payment system forcing the banks to fund their loans
through securitization and other kinds of market means getting rid of the fed
as a not just as a as a clearing mechanism but even as a creation of the unit of account
would be hugely beneficial finally i want to emphasize that doesn't mean that you couldn't do
counter cyclical policy the way that the fed affects the economy during recessions to try
to counter recessions is that it it all operates through an interest rate spread basically
by exchanging reserves for treasuries it really that's its whole mechanism it's affecting the yield
on treasuries by exchanging reserves for treasuries that's what the fed does that's it in a nutshell
well you could imagine a fiscal authority constructed in the same kind of independent
way as the fed that would instead just tax and subsidize loans to affect loan spreads so you
could just say oh you know we're in a recession uh from now on when you're paying a loan on your
consumer debt or your mortgage you're paying let's say x percent we're going to now tell the
government's going to pay five percent of your x and then that will make economic activity happen
more and then if we think the economy is going too fast the government taxes it the interest rate
adds to the interest you pay by five percent so we could imagine using just as we operate on the
interest rate spread between treasuries and cash we can operate on the interest rate spread
in loan contracts with a physical device so I just want to emphasize
there isn't just there is no real need in fact it's kind of straight these central banks that
have been operating for the last um in the world let's say about 150 years there's just no reason
to think that this is the technology we need for the payment system or for counter cyclical policy
or for lending for that matter of course they are an entrenched interest
and all of the decisions about what our financial system can be our political decisions
we can't fool ourselves this is not about technology technology is required but not sufficient
I think what's fascinating about everything you just said is just on the back of mass tokenization
and stablecoins where basically the entire u.s. economy has converted to you know blockchain and
crypto uh for this what sort of new unit of account types of things you could dream up that's what's
fascinating you're also making the point that from a monetary policy perspective there might
actually be more tools at the disposal of monetary uh monetary authorities than there were previously
these kinds of political um like notions these these ideas now that stablecoins are here in the
u.s. do you have any sense for how they'll play out in other sovereign countries other nation
states let's say so like it's a great question you're going to do what's china going to do it
seems like europe has been moving direction let me make a recommendation sure if you haven't had
louis garicano on your program okay louis garicano is a professor at the l.s.c and he is uh the authority
on the european political struggle over stablecoins right now okay and so you should you should have
him on to talk about what they're doing my understanding so in europe the incumbent banks are even more
powerful within the state than they are in the u.s. and they are very much blocking progress
trying to create a banking monopoly of stablecoins too is kind of the way it's heading in europe
uh what what would that mean just like one uh issue i mean in the u.s you don't have to be
an incumbent bank to run the stablecoins but in europe that's kind of the way it's being done
that's my understanding so have louis come and talk to you he's he's more knowledgeable than
anyone on this topic uh but i think that here's what my um training and knowledge from history
tells me countries are all different from each other so let me give you an example
how many countries can you name in the world that have managed for the past 30 or 40 years
to not have a banking crisis and to have a very rich sort of credit to gdp ratio that is they
have a very highly functioning banking system with a lot of credit available and no banking
crises and so i would say at least switzerland is one that probably comes to mind okay switzerland
has had a banking crisis oh they have okay yeah yeah so yeah now i'm out of ideas yeah
i would i would my my second go-to's would be something like singapore but you're close
malta would be one malta would be one um singapore would be one so i'm just going to use those
couple of examples what do malta and singapore have in common they're very small they're small
but it's not just a size thing but the size creates the more important characteristic which homogeneity
banking systems are political foot political footballs the coalition of the winning coalition
of the game of bank bargains is all about taking money from the losers
but if you're homogeneous you don't play the banking game that way so much
because there isn't an identifiable group of losers to steal from which is what bank charters
in the u.s have always been a mechanism to build a coalition that takes from someone else
and preserves our stability at their expense now and that's what we've done that's what most
countries do so there are going to be some countries that are going to figure out hey we're a small
homogeneous country we don't use our banking system as a way to build a coalition that takes
from others within our country and so maybe we should be like a global player in stablecoins
and create all the advantages of a chartered stablecoin system with international access
the challenges these backward corrupt countries like the united states and western euro
so that's where it gets interesting and then will the united states and western europe then
try to put pressure on those countries not to do that so it's a question like why isn't singapore
more active in trying to create a mechanism that could work it in the u.s but with somehow
i mean so the genius act kind of prevents some of this already but i think you can see what i'm
getting at that there's going to be different countries are going to have different strategies
depending on their own political economy and i haven't got a great forecast for how all that's
going to play out but it's it's going to be interesting to watch you're going to see in the mirror
of stablecoin legislation and chartering you're going to see the mirror of that country's political
economy. Charles how do you think this all plays out maybe for the dollar so as we you know bring
this episode to a close let's talk about the the powerful network effect that the dollar has today
which is it is the world reserve currency it's used by the vast majority of payments above 70
percent and then treasuries are the world reserve asset at least right now there's maybe you know
some move to other harder type assets and we we see ebbs and flows of of that throughout history
you said in the short run this is going to help the dollar i can't help but agree right this is
going to dollarize economies around the world that basically have a subpar local currency and
they far rather use the dollar and we're starting to see some of that but long term how does this
play out i think it plays out it depends of course on how the dollar is constructed
you could even imagine creating something called a global dollar so you know there have been such
things like again the bank of Amsterdam you know created abstract units of currency
we could create a domestic dollar and an international dollar like a global dollar like an
sdr type of idea no it's but it's more like trying to be based in a global consumption bundle so
suppose that this future that i'm talking about happens where we use the the recordation of
transactions in the blockchain to create a better unit of account than the Fed's liability treasuries
will be denominated in that account international transactions will be the dollar it'll still be
called the dollar it'll just be a better dollar so you can even imagine constructing not just a new
England dollar a southern dollar a US dollar which is a weighted average of those but you can imagine
creating a global dollar as a unit of account which would have a teal by virtue of the fact that it is
more linked to the global consumption bundle or maybe you could create a dollar for each major
region of the world so if you really wanted to compete give that how does Amazon compete for
business in another country it tries to do something that that people in that country might find
beneficial so maybe if we want to compete to preserve the role of the dollar maybe one way to do it
is to make the dollar better i know that never occurred to a damn politician but it does occur
to people in the business community well stable coins are better dollars because they have better
payment rails so in that sense we're making it better but you're saying that's a medium of exchange
okay but i'm talking about a unit of account i'm saying sure in the short term as we go to more
stable coins that will strengthen the dollar because stable coins will find that by denominating
dollars they they will they will spread more right and more countries and people but the longer term
issue is what about this unit of account and i know a lot of people wonder well if we got rid
of the fed would we even have a dollar of course we would would the dollar be competitive in international
markets would people still want to hold treasury sister reserve assets yes you in fact you can make
the dollar better you could even create a dollar by making it legal tender in the u.s you could create
an international dollar you can even create a european dollar that's legal tender in the u.s
for transactions between europe and the u.s that would be more attractive to the europeans
than the current dollar so the point is if you really want to strategically build
this on this reserve currency advantage that we have why not actually try to create a better
parameter well can i can i ask you on this because you you're emphasizing a better unit of um exchange
basically medium of exchange sorry with with stable coin payment networks better unit of
accounts and innovation there but what about the other function of the dollar which is store of
value and i think like people worry about that i mean look at our deficit this year you know two
trillion dollars and it's continuing to escalate and debt to gdp continues to go up well are we worried
about that yeah so that's that's not about the dollar that's about treasuries that's about assets
are stores of value so yes the dollar the physical dollar is one of those but if you had stable coins
that were denominated in dollars and if the dollar then becomes this inflated thing then people might
decide not to denominate stable points isn't that kind of where we're headed it is actually i've
written an article about this too uh it's it's called um fiscal dominance that is the fact that our
fiscal uh policy is inconsistent with low inflation that's a separate issue and what it tells you is
though another advantage to making to creating a consumption bundle definition of the dollar
if we did if we did that suppose it right now it's not my fingers and my vision of the future can
happen all of our transactions are denominated our consumption bundles there's no longer this
physical thing called the federal reserve currency well that means that we no longer where do we get
inflation from when the u.s. government has too much debt and the federal reserve has to print
money to buy the debt because no one else wants to that's where inflation comes from well if you
don't have a federal reserve what happens when a government issues too much debt it doesn't have
anyone printing money under its thumb to buy its debt right so what does it do it defaults
it defaults that sounds scary that's how scary countries defaulting let's do it all the time
i mean you know and that's better in your in in your mind you're like mind then kind of the slow
over time default and deleveraging that we basically i'm not saying that i'm not saying that i know
it's better i'm just pointing out that if you're worried about inflation coming from the government
debt and i am and by the way my estimate of the inflation rate depending on accompanying policies
if we don't solve our fiscal problem we're going to have at least let's say uh 10 percent rate of
inflation a year and i would say more realistically it's kind of complicated to explain it maybe as
much as 30 percent 40 percent inflation per year like cpi right exactly that's that's what you know
that's that's what the arithmetic tells you it has to be if you don't fix the government debt
problem now uh my st louis federal reserve i have a paper in 2023 published by the st louis fad review
it basically explains that you have me on for another time i'm happy to explain that but um so
yeah that's a pretty high inflation um you could say well which would i prefer having a u.s government
default on its debt when it runs out of room to issue debt or being able to inflate its debt away
well that's a choice i i'm just pointing out that if you went to blockchain based unit of account
then you wouldn't have the government with the option to inflate away the debt it would have to
default but maybe that would mean it's more likely for the government to do something different
which is called fix the problem maybe you know uh so your generation of course is going to be
completely screwed i mean you guys are really idiots if you ask me like why you haven't been out there
with pitchforks and torches and you let these organizations like the aarp by the way if the bpi
bank policy institute is darth vader i think that the aarp is like darth vader's captain that was
strangled whatever his name was general something right they're pretty bad too and they they make it
sound like we older people have this all oh we've paid this money no no no no Medicare benefits
and Social Security benefits for for this current generation that are getting it far far exceed
what they paid in and because something doesn't come from nothing what this means is the very
generous welfare state that is created for me is not going to be available for you because i'm
stealing from you that is real that is not just some of that is not that's arithmetic right
how come you guys don't seem to know how to advocate for yourself how does donald trump
or the entire democratic party get away with just avoiding talking about this
how do they do that well charles i can tell you what we do which is we buy bitcoin instead
that's our protest that's not good enough this is the problem right i said this at the beginning
if you don't understand that everything is politically contingent you can't isolate
yourself you live in the united states you you're earning a salary and it says you're like
you don't you don't insulate yourself by doing some like tech bro nonsense okay
sorry david i i have to tell you you have to organize and play the game and gate and you haven't done
it your generation hasn't done it and i'm really sorry i won't be a member of the aarp under any
circumstance i regard them as a horrible or selfish organization the worst example of that
kinds of thinking that people of my generation and others are capable of because it's so selfish
and so purposely mindless of others thoughtless about others so we need to start raising the level
of our political discussion ethically you know we just had this terrible event of charlie kirk's
death i didn't agree with everything charlie kirk said i thought he was too much of a
trump kiss ass to be honest even though i loved so much of what he did i'm being honest you know i
admire charlie and i i also pray for him and i think very very highly of him but you know we
don't think for ourselves neither the democratic party which is a bunch of corrupt you know
cynical losers nor the mega a sort of pretense that tariffs are good don't worry about the debt
like what's going on with our country you guys you're the blame if you want to know who to blame
look in the mirror that's hilarious because i think a lot of people in our generation probably
blame you know baby boomers for like uh where we are right now no but but the point is this is a
political game engage engage i won't be part of that i agree with you the baby boomers have
selfishly stolen from you you know you don't just buying bitcoin and could have solved that problem
bub i think that's a fair call to action charles uh you know thank you for that uh
admonition as we as we in this episode um i guess maybe my last question for you before we let you go
is do you think we have won sufficiently with the genie spill signed do you think we have won
i know there's going to be political battles ahead but have we won enough such that stable coins
though the horses left the stable they're going to keep running we're going to get into the trillions
of dollars it's like it's no you don't think we've won yet on stable coins i think it's i think it's
a great first step but now you've actually put stable coins into the arena now what's going to
happen once you put them in the arena what will the next congressional bill about stable coins be
you think this is it that would be like saying that when the national banking system was created
that that prohibited jesse jackson from making so much money off of bank mergers in the 1990s
it didn't you never sleep politicians in there and their coalition never sleep
and you better not be sleeping either i guess the cost of um freedom is ever present vigilance i
i guess that's uh that's the message to the end my personal worry as well in addition to that is
that some of the new crypto organizations around stable coins become more and more bank like in
the future it is interesting that entities like circle and tether they get to keep that 4% yield
right now and you sort of wonder like do they really want to give that up it's not inside of
the line no that's what competition will do yes that's what and you know that that's what we need
we need competition which will will get them to relinquish that yield and that's the future that
we're really all hoping for you know that the little guy doesn't have a representative in
washington unless he insists on it by organizing and has clear vision understand of history
i don't say cynical but i say realistic and i don't trust any of those politicians
and i don't think the organized groups that are lobbying in washing generally really are
informed and have aligned interests with you know the average person so you really you know you
have to somehow convince people it's it's very hard because we all have our own jobs we all have
our lives you know how much time can you take out so the answer is you have to come up with a
credible delegation of this interest and they have to have money they have to have political power
that comes for money and influence and having a great network of people who will pressure
politicians um so i think we're already seen a little bit of that but it's very fragile you know
this is not something that you can say oh well we've won the battle oh no you never win the battle
you have to be ever vigilant as you just said and you know i think you know in that's something
you know in memory of and in in gratitude to charlie kirk who i think very highly of
i think that's a good way for us to be thinking he was somebody who really went out there
and did that and had a huge effect but he had an organization you know turning point and we need
we need to be thinking about that we need to think about how to really create intelligent
organizations that aren't captured by incumbent interests and that really can put forward
our collective interests and that means fiscal lobbying and that means protecting crypto from
being seized by some other special interests the whole history of banking is great ideas bank
checking account for a great idea in the 19th century loans were a great idea um lines of credit
with the scott's which the scott's invented in the 18th century great idea these are all great
but they all have to work through the political process and then they get captured and transformed
stablecoins are the same thing great technology blockchains are great technology
don't believe for a minute that you're immune to the government that you can operate in the cloud
or something you know you operate off of a machine and that machine is governed by us law
you you can't escape it and we need to really get engaged
anyway that's my view well it called action then charles and i got to say i didn't expect you to
be um you know so close to the bankless movement as uh as you have been in this discussion so it
sounds like you are no fan fan of banks and are looking forward to their disruption by crypto so
on that count we're uh we're allies on that for sure cut completely bankization gotta let you know
none of this has been financial advice crypto is risky you could lose what you put in but we're
headed west this is the frontier it's not for everyone but we're glad you're with us on the bankless
journey thanks a lot and thank you charles thank you bye guys bye